okay i should be able to see where it
comes on
welcome to meditating and with john
raviki and we're on the part of the
course called
cultivating wisdom in which we're
emphasizing the western wisdom tradition
that runs through
uh epicureanism into stoicism and then
into neoplatons
epicureanism is our primary school
stoicism is our high school
and neoclatinism is our university and
this is the complement
uh to uh the meditation meditating the
john brevaiki series
where we covered a whole course of
practices
uh drawn from the eastern tradition
primarily buddhism but also
important elements from taoism so
welcome uh this
is uh a course that is designed to give
you
a deeply enriched repertoire of
practices
and show you how they coordinate
together in various ways
and then the idea is not that you're not
expected to practice all of these
practices
the idea is give you a rich repertoire
from the eastern tradition
these traditions a rich repertoire from
the western traditions
various ways in which they can be
configured
curated constellated together so that
you can build for you
a rich ecology of practices that will
help you
as you attempt to deal with the
perennial problems of deception
the perennial aspiration to enhance our
sense of connectedness
to ourselves to each other and the world
so welcome
if you haven't done all of the
meditation and contemplation course uh
please
look for description links in the
description of this video you'll find
links
right all the way back to lesson one i
will recommend going
there immediately and doing lesson one
do
one or two lessons a week uh keep
meeting here
uh on what's called the saturday sanga
at 10 a.m
eastern time and what you can do is you
can catch up with the eastern tradition
and then integrate it out with the
western tradition
so it's great pleasure to be here and
as always we're going to begin first by
doing a sit together
so please get yourself into a
comfortable position
we're we're gonna have a timer for about
15 minutes
we'll begin as always with some chanting
and then we'll move into the silence set
once that's done we'll come out of it
perhaps you will recite the five
promises to yourself
there'll be a slight adjustment we're
trying yet another configuration here
um i'll move my my map my pillow out of
the way we'll bring in the whiteboard
and then we'll have the dharma talk
about
the psychologic the psycho ethics
and the psychophysics of stoicism
next week will be our last week on
stoicism next week i'm
going to show you uh through the
wonderful work of bizarre
she has attempted to reconstruct some
stoic meditations
meditative practices so we'll meet and
we'll go through
a couple of those that will be our final
um lesson on stoicism
so if you want to start reading the
third degree of wisdom
in the wisdom of hypatia by mclennan as
we start to prepare ourselves
for the university of neoplatonism
please do
all right so one more time get yourself
ready
we'll begin together when i say begin we
will begin with chanting
begin
on
[Music]
one
[Laughter]
[Music]
one
[Laughter]
[Music]
one
on
[Laughter]
[Music]
one
on
begin your silences
you
so
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition
character and communitas perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
okay
okay i'm just going to move things out
of the way get the whiteboard set up and
then jason will slightly adjust the
camera
give us a moment while we do this we're
still working on trying to get the
hardware in the software
for the two camera setup
[Applause]
thank you son all right
so just wait for the cucumber to focus
good so we're we're doing stoicism and
we're following through mcclellan and
i'm
um i'm supplementing that with some
excellent work uh
from bazaar's book on stoic spiritual
exercises
and we'll finish next week with i think
her very insightful attempt to
reconstruct
uh some stoic meditative practices but
let's finish
uh some of the overall orientation of
the cultivation of wisdom according to
stoicism
and basically we're looking at the idea
of sowistism
as training in aspirational
rationality
rationality again is not just about
the use of logic within argumentation
it's much more comprehensive than that
it has to do with the comprehensive
endeavor to systematically become aware
of
and ameliorate self-deception and to
help us
aspire to become more virtuous where we
understand virtue as the beauty of
wisdom
virtue is how we are wise in any
particular
situation the idea here is is that
that is something that's going to awaken
up
to the process of co-identification
which is at the center
of stoicism and alleviate moodle
confusion
and it is also going to be
the process by which we can
bring about the changes in our cognition
that are needed to ameliorate the ways
we suffer
from how we miss set our heart on things
so this notion of
aspirational rationality is what we've
been talking about
throughout
and we reviewed some of the core ideas
of stoicism and some of the preliminary
well not preliminary
basic practices there that's a better
way of putting it and we've talked about
how there's
basically three aspects to it now
traditionally it's called the logic the
ethics and the physics
but i like to call it the psychologic
because again it's not just about the
logical control
of argumentation it's about the
reflective control
of attention in fact control isn't even
the right word
i like hedo's work the reflective
disciplining of attention
the disciplining of ascent the
disciplining of action
so these are the things we're actually
disciplining and then along the way
we will discipline uh argumentation
we talked about this last time about the
idea of
crisis that's okay um into
the process of epilege
so we're we're trying to bring in
judgment a critical change
uh remember that that this means
um the destabilization but also
opportunity
so all the meanings if you can combine
our our current meanings
of crisis and judgment and opportunity
that's what's actually being carried in
this word
and we're trying to introduce this into
the epilega
so remember we get these impressions and
we have no control over them they're
just part of the nature
and the outcome of the machinery of our
perceptual
uh processing or uncogni or unconscious
processing
and it just gives us impressions but
what we can
intervene on what we can introduce
crisis in the ancient sense into is
all of the epileegan all of the ways in
which we're doing something analogous to
talking to ourselves
remember what antisthenes said that what
socrates what he learned from socrates
was how to more appropriately talk to
himself
this was the stoic interpretation of
this you internalize socrates which is a
perspectival
and participatory transformation it's
something aspirational
in order to learn how to properly become
aware of
and manage this and so
the point about this of course is to get
to
the possibility of a poke uh which i
mentioned
is also a central practice within
phenomenology coming out of
his role he uses that term explicitly by
the way
and i recommended don id's book on
experimental phenomenology to give you
uh if you want to deepen your
understanding and practice of this this
is the idea of
bracketing the impressions and what
we're doing is we're
holding um we're withholding of sort of
immediate ascent
and assertion so
this comes up right there's an
impression and there's a part of me that
starts
talking to myself and saying ah that's a
marker it's a good marker
so right so uh and then so there's an
assertion here
a mental assertion and i ascend to it
and i right and all of this is happening
remember
in a confused fashion in that all of
that is happening
automatically it's happening
unconsciously and it's getting fused to
the impression
and i'm treating them all as one and
what i want to do is defuse this
and when i want to break break it apart
well is it really uh
marker and should i think of it as good
and and of course what you want to do
initially you might have to coach
yourself with that
inner speech but the point is not the
inner speaking
the point is ultimately to introduce
this into it the point is to get
the skill and ultimately the
virtue of being able to
make sure that you are coming
to the best possible assertion
to which you can give the most
reflective ascent
in the situation right you don't you
don't want to be hamlet always just sort
of stop reflecting
but right to what uh your impressions
are
presenting to you so remember the
impressions are just
present and then we represent
them to ourselves in a certain way and
it's
it's exactly in that moment when we go
from the impression
to representation that we want to
intervene
we want to develop crisis judgment
opportunity destabilization defusing
so that we can engage in pocket
and so we've been talking about that
and we then moved into
the beginning of the talk around the
discussion about the stoics meant
about physics or what i want to call
psychophysics because again and again
and again i want to emphasize
it's about how we are making sense of
things
so it's unlike modern physics um where
we're just trying to
right concentrate on the sense made
we're trying to get the best
possible interpretation of the world
that's
all right so that process is always
going on either
explicitly in scientific physics or
implicitly as we move around the world
but what the stoics want us to focus on
is we want we want to learn the best
science we can here
but we want to pay attention to the way
we have internalized that
and to what degree we have internalized
it well in our
interpretive judgments so this is
typically known as this is the
training of desire this is and what that
means is
right the the the the sets of
wants and needs and drives and
motivations
that emerge from how we deem the world
to be
so there's a lot of things there that
we're engaged in
in order to train desire uh we talked
last time
about uh what i was taught to call
objective seeing
what mclennan calls physical description
which rosario calls
uh no bizarre calls physical description
but cloning calls neutral description
and so the idea here is when i am
confronting some situation uh what's
typically
happening is i'm investing it or to use
more modern language i'm projecting
into it um all kinds of meanings
and values that insofar as
i'm desiring the object now remember
desire is is meant here broadly means
uh both how i'm desiring the object but
i may also be desiring the removal of
the object
because it could be something painful or
unpleasant or unwanted
or disagreeable etc so what i'm doing in
the psychophysics
and especially with the uh objective
seeing
is i'm trying now to withdraw projection
so in the epoche right in the
in the psychologic i'm trying to
withhold ascent and assertion
in the psychophysics i'm trying to
withdraw projection
and so what is the most prominent kind
of projection
that we need to step back and withdraw
from and this comes from
again the stoic idea part of it of
course is modal confusion
and those are broad themes but one of
the things i've
talked about most was we want to
withdraw
narrative projection
so narrative projection is right
to see a story unfolding and a story is
always a way of interpreting a situation
according to desire
and so one of the things for example how
i try to practice this
and it's it's a challenging practice for
me but it's a very good practice
i'll be in a situation and will
something will happen and i'll get angry
and i'll realize you know you know
uh you know i can't move this i hate
doing this i start to tweak
as if there's a story here as if this is
an agent as this is it
as if it has motives and what i do is i
step back
and i say wait there's no story going on
here there's no agent
going on here all there is is my desire
for a certain outcome so i would draw
the projection
i'd leave i i let the art we say this
but
and this heidegger took this from
meister eckhart the laser knight
i let this is i'm trying to get you to
understand this very deeply i hope i
hope i'm
being successful i let the objects
be as they in are they
as they those objects are in themselves
that's the physics i let them
be in my practice with objective seeing
right or physical description or neutral
description i can bring that in and say
no
all it is here's a you know a certain
amount of matter
taking up this and that helps me
withdraw narrative projections
and we we like narrative a lot and in
fact when people
often when i first present this to
people they get upset and they say well
no but uh like narrative is narrative
and narrative and myth and story and
all of that is important and as many of
you know i talk about that at length
but what the stoics remind us is
something that i hope has become clear
through a lot of
what we've been learning the processes
that make us
adaptive are the very processes
that subject us to self-deception
narrative is adaptive it helps us to
extend
our sense of time and identity
so that we can engage in long-term
planning
and we can better understand human
motives in situations
and we can better uh pick up on people's
character
this is all valuable stuff totally
valuable
but again the central lesson that which
makes us adaptive
is also that which is right the source
of our self-deception
and so a lot of the time we are engaging
in narrative projection
and so what we want to do is we want to
stop and withdraw that and
let things be fuseus
that's where we get the word physics
who's this means how things spring out
of themselves how they grow
of themselves how they are
self-organized independently
of me and that's important
uh precisely because as i said we even
create entire
popular culture forms of entertainment
that try and tell us that narrative is
in some
secret complicity with the fundamental
laws of nature
like you're in a great love story and
the universe will work
to make sure that the lovers find each
other
and that the the obstacles overcome and
that is all
it's all wishful that's not we
know
at some level but we say well it's just
entertainment the problem is
parts of your brain don't distinguish
between entertainment
and real perception it is hard for you
for
if i do the following for you ask you to
you're in a room ask you imagine doing
something
and then i asked you four weeks later
did you do that something or did you
only imagine doing it you won't be able
to tell the difference
okay so it's very very important
to try and as much as possible practice
the psychophysics the objective scene
helps us to do this of withdrawing
projection
we also uh did the view from above
and the view from above gets you to
withdraw from the first person
perspective
so you're withholding right you're
withholding ascent and assertion
in this psychologic and the
psychophysics one thing you're doing is
you withdrawing
right you're withdrawing projections and
another one is you withdrawing from
the first person perspective in the view
from above
because that affords you taking a more
comprehensive perspective
so that you can do something analogous
to internalizing
the sage so
there are other practices for the
psychophysics one that is recommended
it's not clear how you do it but it's
analogous to some of the buddhist
practices
you periodically reflect and remind
yourself
on how interconnected everything is how
interconnected everything is
and then aligned with that the stoics
again very similar to the buddhists
uh had us constantly remember
how impermanent everything is and the
idea is these two things are actually
um uh different sides of the same coin
we like the first one everything's
interconnected oh that's fantastic
but the thing the fact that everything's
interconnected means that every
nothing is completely self-sustaining
everything is down to everything else
and therefore everything is ultimately
impermanent
so the stoics have a very challenging
practice
associated with this pre-meditation
and what's pre-meditation pre-meditation
is the act
it's kind of like it's analogous in its
application not in its content
to how you apply the five training
precepts the five training precepts
are ways of trying to create
opportunities for applying mindfulness
and realizing wisdom uh in
pre-meditation what you do
is you practice again this is
the way you're talking to yourself dear
logos with yourself
you practice reminding yourself of
the fatality of all things fatality
doesn't mean just mortal right
it means that everything is ultimately
finite
subject to failure and subject
to impermanence in a way that is beyond
your control beyond my control beyond
our control
and so the stoics have some very they um
have some very challenging practices
around this
and it's recommended by buzari and i i
agree with this you don't start with
pre-meditation
you do this after you've been doing all
the other practices
but when you kiss your beloved
good night say to yourself i'm kissing
immortal
i'm kissing a mortal
when you see one of your cherished
objects here's you know
i really really uh you know like these
shoes
this is a thing that will pass away
these shoes that i like so much will
pass away
see the idea is to stop and remind
yourself
that everything everything you're
encountering even
even the most beloved of things are
impermanent in fact your love
doesn't render them permanent
we want to believe it does
we really do we have myths around that
like that somehow love gives us
an access to the permanence of things
but the stoics challenge that and they
say all that it's
ultimately permanent and eternal it's
the logos of the universe that's sort of
there and now
they're they're god it's that the
ongoing patterning of reality that makes
it intelligible
for us and makes it a possible arena
in which we can cultivate wisdom and
virtue that
for the stoics the logos
that which gathers together and orders
everything
so that our logos via logos
is possible that is what is eternal for
the stoics everything else
is constantly arising and passing away
and in that sense
it is very similar to buddhism and the
the doctrine of impermanence and
non-open and many people have noted
that and so the the stoics
try to get you to the point here is not
to crush your love
that's that it's almost it is that's a
mistake remember in the middle
in buddhism in the middle path right
it's not it's you're not
you're trying to get in between
self-indulgence and self-denial
the point here is not to deny your love
it's to realize your love
it is to realize that you are loving
immortal
that doesn't mean you should stop loving
it means you should pay attention to
how you are loving and what you what
kind of entity you are loving
and what kind of entity you are as a
lover
so pay attention to all the things
you love and the pre-meditation
is to remind yourself that tomorrow
or later today they could be gone
absolutely
completely without remainder without
recall without recollection
this is a hard practice like i said i do
not recommend
yeah just start this right now i think
you should be doing all of the
i think you should have done a lot of
meditation a lot of contemplation
both sit it and moving exercises i think
you should be doing
the view from above a lot i think you
should be doing objective seeing a lot i
think you should be doing all of the
self examination processes the
journaling
the cultivation of active local
mindedness you have to do that a lot
and then you start to practice the
pre-meditation
because only then will you have the
depth of responsiveness
so that you can be responsible to the
reality
of the fatality of all things
so the last as i've mentioned is the
psycho ethics
this is the training of impulse or the
training of action
i don't have too much to say about that
because we've already been practicing
that from the very beginning
that's the primarily what you're trying
to do is you're trying to cultivate
virtue
where virtue is understood as the beauty
of wisdom virtue is the way
of uh most realizing how to bring
principal
sophia into the situation
phronesis so that i can act most wisely
in that situation it is
it is it is a kind of um getting
the optimal grip of beauty in action
uh that renders our actions increasingly
more and more
wise and increasingly more and more
virtuous
but also increasingly more and more
beautiful one of the great things that
plato reminds us
um in the republic but sorry in the
symposium but also in the republic
is that we should eventually move from
physical beauty the beauty of particular
people or objects
to realizing the beauty of virtue which
is
the beauty of a life well lived
and really what is more beautiful
than a life well lived well if you think
about it that way then
if the greatest beauty is a life well
lived
then virtue is the beauty
of wisdom and so what
what are the practices there well you
know them already they're the practices
of self-examination that we've been
talking about
from the very beginning you know at the
beginning of the day setting your
intention what do i intend to do today
um you know you're doing this already
when you're for example doing
uh the five uh training precepts
at the end of the day you check your
journal right and you reflect on
you know any vices you committed any
virtues you omitted
any bias you were able to detect and
right um any virtue you remember having
engaged in
always end with that because it's a
positive it's a motivating it shows you
like you're trying to get between um
arrogance and despair
by getting a balance of noticing your
errors
and your successes and so you want to
the project of cultivating wisdom
is the project that springs from deep
self examination and a constant
reflection on a daily basis
of how virtuous you have been throughout
the day
so that's the basic that's the basic
stoic setup you what you've got
is you've got these pro practices and
there's more practices you can
read some more in there's many books as
i've indicated on stoicism
i'm trying to give you a core ecology
what i think the core ecology
of practices is for stoicism you know
what you can do for the psychologic
the training of judgment uh what you can
do for the psychophysics the ch
the training of desire and what you can
do for the psycho ethics
the training of impulsive action and
there's a lot more there
you could read pierre hedoe's uh inner
citadel which is a great reflection i
also
recommend strongly start reading
on the meditations by marcus aurelius
seneca's letters a picture to his
discourse
and on the manual for living the manual
for living makes
excellent uh lectio divino uh
material the sodas marcus aurelius's
meditations
next week we will round this all out uh
because and i want to
tap into pizari's excellent i think it's
a very good reconstruction
i'm trying to do something similar i'm
trying to reconstruct neoplatonic
dialectics she's tried to reconstruct
um stoic meditative practices and so
that will be the final
sort of culminating thing we can do how
what you can do in an acidic practice
you already have one
other view from above but she she has a
few more she's gonna
uh share with us i'll share them with
you and then we will then be on the
doorstep
of neoplatonism we'll be on the doorstep
we'll be ready to graduate
into the university of new plateaus
okay so what i'm going to do now is i'm
just going to turn slightly to a
sign i apologize that this is a little
bit odd but i need to take a look at any
of the questions
we might have um and
so i've got all this stuff here i'll
i'll go over i'll read the question
and then i'll come back okay is this
anything like ed slingerland's trying
not to try research
or something very different um
so well that's from robert great it's
similar
in in some senses um in that
you're trying to get to a place of
prochyron
where this is your this is your as we
even have a phrase for this which is
very helpful this is your second nature
so that it becomes
natural to you uh to flow with
the flow of reality as much as possible
so as reality shifts and changes
you stay continuously coupled to it and
that
is thought to be the experience of joy
i do think though that there are
significant differences between taoism
we're trying not to try
is i think the central thing and
stoicism
which has a much more deliberative
top-down aspect
i i recommend and this is what i found
in my own
uh practice that the eastern traditions
tend to be more
emphasized bottom-up and that's why they
emphasize the spontaneous emergence and
the trying not to try
you see that i think at the core of
buddhism and taoism
the western traditions are much more uh
top down and deliberative and
they're much more disciplined in the
sense of the discipline originally means
following it doesn't mean
punishing it means following and
learning it doesn't mean punishing
they're disciplining their top down
discipline and given what i know as a
cognitive scientist i think
it's very clear you need both the bottom
up buddhist and daoist strategies that's
why i've been teaching them to you
but you need the top down epicurean
stoic
and neoplatonic strategies the
interesting thing about the neoplatonism
as we'll see
is that what it basically does is it
sort of takes the top down
um to its limit so that it flips and
inverts to be
completely bottom up and there in many
ways
many people have noted this you know dt
suzuki and others
uh the deep similarities between
neoplatonism and buddhism for example
vita perez is asking what is the name of
the stoic meditation authors he's
referred to
here i'll bring the book out and say it
again
so this is ellen busari stoic spiritual
exercises
alain buzari stoic spiritual
exercises oops i think i hit the camera
out that's okay
um there's a question from the
tricer or the tricker uh i find it odd
that we are digging most of the wisdom
from ancient creeks and since
there was no one who was a new age plato
or aristotle or any other one
am i ignorant in this i'm not quite
understanding the question let me read
it again i find that we're digging most
of the wisdom from the ancient greeks
and since then there was no one who was
who was a new age plato
or aristolees or anyone am i ignorant to
this
um so i i i understand your question now
the this has to do with a very long
um historical argument about why
philosophy as philosophia the
aspirational and communitarian love for
wisdom
that we are practicing right here right
now why
that fell into advance and why
philosophy instead
until very recently became this very
technical uh conceptual analysis
in order to address epistemological
concerns around skepticism
or the nature of science i i i i
have got degrees in academic philosophy
i think it gives me a valuable set of
skills
but what academic philosophy until very
recently didn't talk about
even though it's in the name of the term
was wisdom and how to cultivate wisdom
so it was the work of people like pierre
hadou who you've heard me recommend a
lot
who have brought back what is ancient
philosophy
and what is it like to practice
philosophy as a way of life
rather than an academic purely
conceptual technical
uh set of skills uh within uh you know
some sort of
academic institution and and so
there have been philosophers who have
uh brought recently or have brought
back um the topic of wisdom
um and have started to uh re-understand
philosophy more as a practice i
mentioned the phenomenological tradition
coming out of his role and this way of
training attention and seeing
and don id's book experimental
phenomenology and then that tradition
went into people like heidegger um and
what you get there is this tremendous um
post height of you get a reflection on a
lot of people trying to cultivate
practices
um in a heideggerian vein that will
allow us to recapture um a lot of what
ancient philosophy
is so my good friend and colleague guy
sandstock has created the circling
practice
as a way of doing that within what what
is still properly called academic
philosophy there has been the return
to the discussion about the cultivation
of wisdom
it's also been taken up very seriously
now within psychology and within
cognitive science and within that
there are a lot of people doing
excellent work both in terms of the
theory
the sophia and the practice the
phromesis of wisdom
so i hope that answers your question if
you want that more long-term historical
analysis
please check out my series awakening
from the meeting crisis
where i take you through the the ancient
greeks and then i show you how this
ramified through christianity
and then how we lost it uh there are
important pivotal figures who try to
recover it one person i
don't get to talk enough about is
somebody who's in the midst of the
scientific revolution
who really tries to recover this wisdom
tradition
and and leave it into the scientific
worldview and that's spinoza so you
might want to take a look at spinoza as
well
so mark lefebre do you have a list of
sources for practices in suggested order
how would i go about building that
needing this for the ecology of practice
schematization
so um i that's something i've been
working on periodically i've
i've been in partnership with people um
and
what happened is that those various
partnerships have been fragmented and
frayed
uh largely because of covet um
it's not stopping in here
mine's also stopped
it's back sorry for that interruption um
mark what i was saying is i i you know
i'm gonna do as much good work as i can
in a top-down fashion but
i'm also hoping to get a lot of feedback
and
you know existential experimentation
within the discord server community
about how things are fitting together
and how pieces fit together
hopefully with with really good and
cooperative philia within distributed
cognition
we can come up with a very good answer
to that very central question
like i said i'm doing some work on it
there's going to be some publication on
it
soon um but there's more that there's
much more that needs to be done
i also recommend we take a look um as a
community at
zac stein's really important work on the
needed transformation in education uh
it's called education and the time
between
two worlds and some of the videos the
discussions i've had with zach
especially as curated by andrew sweeney
might be valuable in that project
okay so um we have a question from
random name
what specific parts of spinoza do you
recommend also have you looked into the
use of peptides or
cognitive enhancer um so i recommend the
ethics
actually i recommend getting the
completed works i recommend
going through the ethics reading a
proposition
and a proof on a daily basis i've done
that a couple of times
um there's a couple of there's a couple
of excellent books
uh on i'm actually going to go off
camera for a sec because i want to get
those books
i hadn't prepared this so please just
give me a second
sorry for that but here's a couple of
excellent books on
so read the ethics and then you there's
the book called the spirit of spinoza
healing the mind by neil grossman
i'll just pull that up for a minute
and then this is interesting especially
when we talked about the pre-meditation
today but
you have to get into spinoza to
understand how he's actually arguing for
a form of stoicism
and neoplatonism but then the next book
is think least of death
spinoza on how to live and how to die by
steve
nadler
then i recommend for the primary text
get the complete spinoza
you could read the improvement of the
understanding you could read the short
treatise which is an excellent place to
begin
much more sort of spiritually written uh
than some of his latest works and then
you can
uh but the main thing to get into is the
ethics
and read that um like read it
religiously read a proposition and a
proof
reflect on it think about it through the
day and then build and build and build
and then try
periodically to to see the whole
in each proposition and then see how all
the prophecies
would fit together to make the whole and
that will give you what spinoza called
sciencia intuitiva you'll see the hole
in the part and the parts in the hole
and then that that suddenly becomes a
lens by which you see the world
and that's a powerful transformation
that the inter
the interaction with spinoza can afford
spinoza is
one of one of the philosophers that i
deeply love
because he represents uh one of the the
epitome
for me of an individual trying to bridge
between spirituality
and science and do it in a profound um
way that is not just something you read
about but as you read spinoza
the act of reading spinoza is like
lectio divina it is a spiritual exercise
that is not only
transforming your belief but
transforming your very ways of thinking
and ultimately your state of
consciousness your very ways of seeing
and being
the only other person that i found that
is like that
is platinus so
i think that's everything for today um
so remember uh we're going to do the
stoic meditations next saturday
saturday sega uh 10 a.m eastern but
i i would advise you to start reading
the third degree of wisdom in the women
as we start to prepare for
neoplatonism um at the university of
neoplatonism
and you're going to find it uh both more
exciting
and also more challenging than both
stoicism and epicureanism at least
that's what i predict
so thank you all very much for your time
and attention and for joining
i hope you keep practicing thank you for
jason for all of his work behind the
scenes
i think this this this new way of trying
to make use of the space
is a little less jarring than the weird
angle uh
we are still working on getting the two
cameras ongoing it's turned out to be a
very hard problem when mar
is really working on it a lot it makes
me appreciate the kind of videos that
people
are put together i've come to a deeper
appreciation of that
so remember continuity of practice
is more important than your quantity of
practice
don't hold yourself to the standard of a
harsh perfectionism but a virtuous
friendship
philia there is no
friend greater than your own mind and
body
no true companion on the path better
than your own
mind and body be lamps unto yourselves
and to each other take good care
everyone
see you next saturday